thank you lineup
easy Massa %uh let's get down to something
more difficult yeah
%uh my name's Jim blame him %um like she
said
%uh my day job is had a biomedical
research facility for doing that genomic
analysis on
worms and flies in other sciences stuff
but
%uh for fun over I like to look at
%uh data visualizations and an interactive
once and today I'd like to
%uh talk about that the force layout
Coloma more detail
and and how to %uh I use it and
in a non traditional manner some so
we're gonna be abusing the force they
are typically
here's %ah here's a you know we just saw %ah
example have your traditional course
layout andy is this is
typically utilize for your social
network or your
congress' voting on the same stuff you
know network based stuff
%um but we're going to abuse this force a
little bit
and come up with some novel ways to
apply it
%ah to other data visualization techniques
to make your %ah life a little bit easier
so for size 12 get everybody on a
baseline of what
what exactly what we're talking about I
mean force layout %um
I think you know for most people work I
would agree that I with the right amount
of notes
in Europe with the right amount above
was in your layout
%um it's a pleasing way it's a pretty
way to draw a graph
%um it but it works underneath the
covers is working as a physical
simulation so you to these notes
is kinda but a charged force are charged
particle excuse me
and they have these charges work to
to move to reports or to attract them in
different ways
and the links between these notes
constrain that movement and the
simulation works as a giant
loop so %uh each iteration each cycle
this loop %ah
the charges are %ah are im
impact the notes they move and visual
display is updated and that looping just
occurs over and over again
until it settles into a stable
configuration
%um so that's that's the force layout
in a not so that's that's how it usually
works I'm a big fan of
this concept that everything is a remix
%uh which I first kinda last onto from
curry ferguson's
a wonderful videos which you haven't
seen %ah
put in your headphones now I'm and so it
wasn't on ignore me
%ah but his his main thesis is that
%um in the art in the creative world %ah
new works are created by simple
modifications of existing work see you
take you take some existing stuff you
copy you transform into you combine %ah at
a great new pieces
and it his his videos are about
that occurring in the arts in music and
and %um
literature and the movies by the good
is also true and I think we've seen this
in a number of presentations
%ah also true and the data visualization
world so
for this stock would like to provide
some remix will components
%uh little nuggets love love useful
you know trickery that that we could
start thinking about
applying to I your own visualizations
so that means we're a look at some code
and of West not a terrible mistake
%um so let's start with the force level
they start out with just
looking at just a note so its build-up
this first probability up a simple no
layout indeed three
id3 is a powerful tool for this because
%ah
I think we'll see the %ah succinct miss
that you can write
and start using that the force laid out
Emilie and
look the chances are you're five using
the three in your other stuff so it's a
good
%uh that it has that and in the talk at
that you could use
%um so like everything in d3 %ah the notes
are going to be represented by some data
so here we have
are just are are basic data says an
array have
objects and he's object has some
attributes here we just have
the and the amount that review together
force layout started
it's pretty easy to create a new
instance a force layout
you pass and your data your notes %um
as the notes parameter and then you
start and then
%um what talk about this year the second
you but you also want to just listen to
the takeover
and that as we'll see allows you access
to
the simulation each iteration each loop
up that simulation
%um an important thing to remember about
d3 and in general and and the
force led and in particular %uh is that
you not constrained by particular Rep
visual representation right that's one
of the big powers on the
up the whole idea but that doesn't mean
you have to do a little bit of extra
work to get things going
so a couple more pieces I've love of
code
%uh first you have to you have to decide
what how you want to visualize your
a force layout so you have to visualize
your
simulation so in these will just use
some SVG circles
%uh but really your keep in mind that
could be anything that will see a couple
examples of other stuff
and right now %uh so yet so you your
binder data
%uh in this case the force nodes to to
that visual representation
and right now we won't use any
attributes so that that it would issue
some static const int for
the radius now inside
when the for sale starts you get %um
your data attributes good injected with
some
variables are some more attributes I if
they weren't very present
and specifically will look at the X&Y
axes view
that body it added to each element have
your data rate
and these represent the current position
have that
a the no did being represented by that
%um
visual at every iteration love the
layout so you can use that to position
your %um your notes and so this is the
text function
this is a the simplest example the tech
function this'll get called executed
every
iteration of the simulation and we can
use the
X&Y from being provided by arse are
forced layout
%um update to move modify the positions of
the
circles the that were using to represent
so with all that you get a you cover get
a couple circles frames
%ah would you can you already see that
this is a nice
%ah visual attractive %ah same
and it only took a few lines of code to
do this so
what what's going on behind the scenes
to help make this attractive are
are the forces that we've mentioned that
are working on it to these notes
I like to talk about briefly a charged
and gravity
charge %uh I get my guy up charge
represents
%um the the reporter attraction between
each node in every other node so %um
a more negative values cause the nose to
repulse from one another
and more and less negative and positive
eyes causing to attract
%um so you are gonna make cool stuff like
that
um gravity on like this forever is not
down to her thats
is moreover events described as a
physical spring
spring-like same attached to the center
%uh the
visualizations so a higher gravity I'm
constrains it to the center and if you
let go of gravity you
everything flows out the space so I'll
just this this beginner introduction
knowledge to
the layout you can start to abuse the
force and our own
in our own way um and the first abuse
can be
%uh the example that irene was talking
about the
the public char and this was first are
one the first so you know best ways
this was shown was a New York Times
visualization that
was looking at the Obama a budget
proposal
and some use in the you know term budget
a bubble charge us to read mean
were using the the node size to
represent some underlying data about you
so how would how we might we
be able to implement this type a
visualization
using the knowledge that we have about
of course layout
well the first date is easy weekend and
city views in some static const int
for rads we can scale the size were
published by
the data that is representing you know
that we wanted to represent on
and that gets us halfway there I but
unfortunately everything's overlapping
nothing looks good anymore
so what we do the the inside is that we
can
passe function to our charge primary
doesn't have to be constrained by ice
data casa neither
and so you can use so this this now
functional get
executed for each node in your layout
I at the start up the force a a at that
start
time and so we can use the date itself
to scale um are are charged are reported
value
by this the amount that is being
virtuous and with those two changes
we did this nice a
affects right each node is is pushing
away a relative
to a its size and the sizes are then
scaled by the day
you're looking for so it was very nice
um and this is my this is
the the summation of the whole talk
so study it %uh
I think Mike Bostock a said it very
eloquently when he said the force lay
out there is an implicit way
to do position encoding I'm gonna remix
that
quote slightly and say it's a lazy way
to move notes around
but its it's a good kind of lazy so on
as we'll see in these these other
examples where we
don't have to care about %uh each
individual location of that
up the no 2 instead impose simple rules
in our simulation right and allow the
notes to find
correct positions based on our simple
rule set that were given a
yeah here we're just using that the
charge the simple rule that charges
relative to size
and that's all it takes so
how ask away abuse this concept to apply
I'm several forces
a yeah ask your nice yeah
I like the Darth Vader is the evil lists
character and yet in the book your the
movie
a well the the original one here
up had this cool feature where but you
could split apart notes based on some
categorical values so here the it's
mandatory versus discretionary spending
which brings us to the idea I love up
imposing our our own are applying it
yeah
a imposing our own custom forces onto
the
the notes so I recreated on
part serve the the New York Times one
a visualization in this up demo for the
for the
blog post about this is gates
spending so the Gates Foundation on so
that time was cut off but
and their then the grant sizes that
they've provided over the years
so and in this the CAG or the character
Oracle
slaying we can do is over years and so
you can see
you get this really nice organic a
feeling
and they came back emerge back together
so it's pretty
a and it's useful so how do we do that
well here's our our basic take function
the whole the whole general idea of
customs forces
in this in this example is we can modify
this slightly
to add enough first day you know a
function at jacks with your notes
somehow
and modifies the in position slightly
and then use that %uh to then that
modify position to them
position are nuts um so here's an
example
I and we all go through all the code but
a
in this we would have some some way to
represent
the two centers that we want to have a
rest let up I know it's
from left to right and out we
grab where you have a function called
move toward center
you know Tagore centre a and this this
is a function that returns a function
will see why
in a minute on but so we grabbed are the
correct
the crank sensor for our particular
nodes by member this is going to get
executed each
if reach node I'm and then
move move that node based on the centers
location so that almost works
here's our are nodes when we when we buy
that
custom force up we're back to everything
its slamming on top of one another so
what's going on with you
we've lost that a nice thing that I just
that was the whole point in this talk
was that we did not care about stuff now
it seems like we don't care about
everyone work position on Alyssa um
fortunately we have this this access to
this
predator which is which is indicated as
alpha
arm now we can think of it as a blending
parameter I that can be used to combine
multiple forces are charges on these
notes
and if we it's accessible from the on
force
instance but you can also get to it from
from the tech function at each iteration
inside of an event
that's faster and if we were to print
those out
we can see that it starts around .1
and gives decker minute slightly every
iteration
above the every loophole that that
simulation and then what it means
um yet what when it gets too up-close
2.05 it'll end
so the numbers are arbitrary but the
idea is that this is
the actual a mechanism by by which the
force layout is
is settling down and two I mean it's
it's the
can be considered a form of simulated
annealing if if you're into that kinda
thing
around but but this is what's causing
the
the stabilization of the force layout
and general
so we can use this parameter and here's
the same code but
instead of a so here now we get to pass
and a
the Alpha into our into our move toward
category centers and with that small
tweaks this is why this is why it's a
function return to function is because
so it allows us to pass and
variables I without creating a global
variable we can pass and locally and
here
and had have access to on in our in our
closer to here
um but with that small tweak veins
now work as you expect now wouldn't work
and not
a here when we separate them out
love the it the alpha blending allows
our
charges that are now relative to the the
size of the notes
to be blended with our custom force and
a works with a lot of nose and works if
you
dragging around though the stick to
their centers but again we're not
were not worried really about where
you to these notes goes we just on time
you guys club here you guys come up here
and they figure things out Scott nice
Tom
so let's look at another iteration of
this
i right now the to the reports in the
charge
that's that's a associate with each
other's noses nice
it keeps them the nodes away from one
another but it
it's kind of an eventual process right
so what if you wanted
that to be a more constrained more
formal
looking a distinction on
where you we're gonna ever mandeville
simple collision detection
in the same manner so this was dunno I
like
remix in New York Times graphics a
and by remix you know where but I
a by this is done by another great piece
where that were visualizing a the words
different words said
at the different national conventions
during the elections
and I R I implemented again support to
this
and another visualization that just
looks at a word frequencies and
and some books but the the point if it
is that now
from when we move these guys around at
the there's
nice hard-line around each in their
their clout in there and they're
um maintaining that a parameter around
them
today implement this a is the same
same idea ennui we use another
I'll modification function we can call
it collide
and I just look at well as look at
pseudocode here on
because the it's not difficult was a
long
so again this has been executed for each
node on at every cycle
%uh that's the that physical simulation
the nose layout
so we just inside this we can loop
through all the other notes
and then do a simple distance check if
if they're too close based on
the the values %uh the data attributes
that we already know
in in those in those nodes that we just
move them back by half
I'll I so we get that I was that
slight modification we can get this nice
look it works with other custom
a forces like them always like that and
it works with
any number of nodes that you put into it
and this this is a a brute-force
mechanism the that you can optimize but
just a starting point for this kind of a
visualization
you can do core stuff like the the demo
of putting an invisible node
underneath your me your mouse cursor and
then every time all your other
little notes are afraid of it just fun
to
okay oh yeah I want more and
there's nothing that mandates that you
have to move them
back by half so if you start increasing
that
that movement you can end up with this
nice but useless popcorn
explosion star colliding with one
another and
getting scared him right away just one
I'll okay so let's say I think this is
Dragon Ball Z not really
a Star Wars buzzer as a force
a let's add some some links you know
finally um with links constrain the
locations
that our notes can move around a
II here's Jersey example with the links
now
and as you might expect the three links
are also represented
and data so the minimum two things you
need in your link data
our source and a target which represent
the two
I know is that they're connecting with
you can do this either via an index into
the nodes are a
or with the actual notes themselves and
if you do in an index
when they're forced layoff starts
they'll be translated into
the notes themselves which means you
have access to
up both the source and target no data
on you need a visualize on some way view
if you so choose and so we can draw
simple line in this example
and then like I said you have access to
the source and destination
our source and target a data and you can
use their X&Y coordinates
to position your lines start/stop
and so and %uh some the simplest the
example I could covers that
a forces also have their own are links
also have their own parameters
I'd like to talk about just link
distance and a
as you might guess like distance just
specifies
the early distance the link the the link
to the links
um a based on
some value so another insight
is you can make that link distance
driven by data sorry instead have been a
constant
it can it can be a
it can represent some data value and
this
in this case the link a data has some
value
distance that you could use to to expand
occurred tracked each like
at upper legs level and that's
essentially all I've done in this
particular
visualization where I was looking that
um
a communities in neighborhoods that have
a sharp racial divide
so here this is Kansas City and each
each node is now represented by census
tract
and like I said today you don't you're
not constrained by
bubbles on sand underneath it and so
each census tract is connected to its
neighbors
by links an invisible links and that
this isn't hasn't started yet
but the link for those links is relative
to the proportion
up a white and black populations between
that mean that neighbor and its neighbor
you know that that
census tract as neighbor so iron
if there's a sharp a jump and
in white or black population so if you
go from one
census tract is 20 percent white to its
neighbor be in 20 percent
black then then that link will be longer
so we start this it it starts to break
apart
at areas where there's this real high
division
and I just I read I is sorry that
you understand kinda a
the medium emotionally intense a value
I want to just kinda look at a way to
represent how these
um a racial boundaries affected the
the first that the spatial a very small
areas in which they occur
so are there's that's a bit that's all
but up
underline that we're just a link
distances you know i trick on their
so we can start expanding these concepts
a and the first the first and I thought
have when
um I'll kinda discovered the multiple
centers
idea as what have you put it into a
circle you know her like circles
so here's my interactive hair ball that
I did
for a I my the
the people that I work with artwork for
as towers they
wanna just got over IRT representation
of collaboration you know what are the
main
science stances everybody climbers with
one another sorry to these
these are these groups is a lab each
node you circle it is a
individual in that lab and there's links
between them
based on how many papers are on together
on
so it's fun and it allows for
exploration again
all I'm defining they are the a route
the cert
the center's along a circle right on for
each slab
%uh not to individuals which means we
can do stuff like
reordering the um the circle center
locations for makes everything move
around you know
kinda fun you can you can change and if
you change the
a the to a radius that your
applying the circle to you can make
pretty but useless you know obviously
artistic a spiral love spiro love
collaboration
s but you get to find out who's who's
the coolest kid in there
India the group there on
if if you want you know %uh a little bit
a mass in turn affect how I feel
embarrassed for need in this country
Myers after their previous stock but
da Mac right has a great introduction to
this a math for pictures which i think
is a
is a wonderful Explorer introduction to
using
up using this kind of math to generate
circles and stuff
another example up from a website called
Let's free congress
that was used is kinda vague extension a
above the idea that are they're looking
at
the small number of people that
contributed large amounts of money
to a to election funding
um but these the visual was kind of
interesting I thought I have recreated
so
you start out with a bunch of nodes I
kinda wanted
Kill Bill new music to be playing at
this that's why the color scheme is such
um and as the sender node expands
the to the the nodes around it are kinda
repulsed
a kinda in a very organic matter right
I i like it and then when you come back
down and they are
jump on I'm but this is
is trivial now that we know um
the previous examples there's all
building on so we can tell
this is a the collision detection is
isn't in effect here
um but it's also just a modification
love the um the charge
right up for that center know it so you
get get a value from your slider
and then modify your charge function to
utilize that
value and on that's all you need to do
to create this kind have
interesting visual where it was again
not much work
the last I like to look into and death
is a
is a ok I have a deviation for Moretz
sterner stuff on earth
um it's called he's got a again have a
buzzer cut bread experiments
and the idea is um you start out with a
grade he represented by these
these dots are kinda hard to see um by
the only
apply force layout diagram and this case
is this random data but
the they have to offer they have to
follow two rules one
they need to stay on on a grid spot
and two um no two nodes can stay on the
same grid spot
so when you started up I
grades is kinda very interesting looking
on patterns them
and a you can modify the
the are the shape up your grid
underlined fears
here's more just rectangle bird and you
can see the
they kinda move those you ask you know
there's little tweaking that goes on as
it as it sits there
and the reason behind that is %uh
there's actually two nodes
associated with each other up with these
are these points the the
from the visual 1 and then this
underline one that still getting
manipulated by the other forces in
effect so you have these two
parameters a are these two roles and
then
and then there's still the charge and
constraints are being applied
to up to these notes
so %uh I was the first a nice thought
when I saw this was
so it's you know subway maps and trans
amass a I kind of wanted a
create that for density so here's
attend city subways works pretty good
right
I a we don't have we don't have
I was further inspired tour and by that
I mean
easy access to data I'll when fathom did
this
this is very similar experiment with the
the Boston
a subway systems here so fat and has a
great post about
how much geography can we get rid of and
in transit maps in self
you know it's a there's a just a thought
process but I really liked
the visual display here so I thought I'd
retry it
with the with this simple
more you know a simpler than it really
define the algorithm that they they use
to it
to create that visual but now we know
the
the algorithm here so we'll start start
each node which is this
a subway station will start them at
their geographic
you know physical location and then
we'll let the simulation run
and see what happens and its interesting
%uh I think it's kind of artistic and
and fun I don't know about the
practically
you know being able to read this item
I'm not from Boston soda
doesn't matter to me but yeah
but it is a event is Elise the starting
point is something to
to conjure up more ideas and I look
forward to seeing some others
um I've got three more
quick examples above up these same
prince was being applied and and
in the real world %uh the first one is a
notre site but is Barack Obama the
president dot com from the
the Guardian right at these bow the the
balloons themselves are a are being
controlled by force last so they have a
up you know buoyancy kinda concept that
are making the flow
and then if you were to hover over one
up on you get the same
radius expanding concept to to a lesser
degree that kinda pushes
and focuses in on one %uh once the one
balloon
I also have I like this one this the
save my library by
us Sarah Groff plum borough UX the
designer I privates for her name and San
Francisco
I I those edges and as a says she's
gonna find
or are making no dove her library her
books actually contains
as is the simple concert again we're
just using
the same idea as multiple Center points
but now with a lot more from
but allows for starting to quantify
these different categories and
in an intuitive way you know the larger
bubble group is
means a larger number books there and
this again is part of a larger
interaction that can be moved around him
and modified
come and explore and finally a
discusses a recent a kinda dash for they
called gravity
where and you to these you to these a.m.
quite nodes represents a a topic
and a the and the bubbles that start
forming around it
are a %uh comments and conversations
around those topics
and the the more the same part is that
this is real time in it and it gets
updated while you watch it but
but it's the same affect really the
notes themselves are part of a force
layout
and each had the and nodes in a
particular
a category are being drawn organically
to to the center which happens to be
there
the right topic no and so
you know whether a little bit of a work
they're allowed they're allowed to have
all this flexibility
from buyer just to find these the civil
rule sets
so hopefully we've seen a little bit
behind the magic
above the force right this is Frank us
you know controlling your right and I'm
school and a um
that was you know I mean point is to
take away some of the magic behind this
I think it's important that on we get to
see the the how of
of summer these you know visualizations
that were inspired by
and and try to the breaking down to
little components that we can then
abuse ourselves so look for your abuses
and I'm thanks
into question oh yes questions
been
yeah
right yeah now I think I think
somebody's arced
again starting points a I love where
the yeah that you concerning coding
iron more you can start applying more
simple rules
to these it to to make them more finesse
um
but I i've seen examples I've way I use
on my ex-wife beam
being part of the it yeah
and and so is i mean there's yeah so
were seen examples where
well in the Obama the the first one here
are
one-third and talk about something that
also makes it
to a to think get to it something that
makes it cool as
a that there are you there actually
doubling code in there
on the color %uh the
when we get to it there
I am color shows the amount
I love cut increase right says but that
is kinda also double encoded by
it that the layer that it's in so I i
really like
that their they're adding that nuance I
don't talk about but so
in this I guess though the Y is you know
at least a hoping that that
that separation by keeping vans layered
and the implementation others you just
add another
I'll custom force and and I could allow
for time but
the nuances that they have they have the
they've multiplied by alpha twice for
that particular for so
the affect the impact love
above the tearing is lest then the
impact of the
separation so you you end up you can
blame them to your own discretion how
much you want the
wonder affect you know the other if you
are both sick or whatever
I thought that was a nice may have made
may be an example where this is
the starting to occur
or
were hmm where
or court yes
yeah I V cool from and im in my
my hair ball are those links art
impacting the the locations of the nodes
but but yeah i certainly a and an easy
optimization to that would sit to be
able to make him the order of those
knows more meaningful and thats
the reordering was was an attempt at
that but utilizing
the data the the date inherent in that
and that is that would be much more
powerful where to to
a start looking at the process
or a
well i think thats depend on the
technology like we've seen
um this same can bog down after
in SVG after a couple hundred nodes and
it did send certainly seems I'm not an
expert but seems to be depended on the
browser you're looking at 2i mean
I I'm doing this in Chrome for a reason
now most it is one flies well and at
least
earlier iterations a Firefox and so the
other browsers
um I know there've been experiments and
using cameras and I think that the
performance can be in
improved after you get a certain head to
a certain threshold um
but I might be incorrect about that %uh
the stock has a
air example if comparing SPG and
and canvas imitations not the force
layout but a bunch of
notes moving around in there a here's
I they they do work in a similar spot
efficiency at
at certain numbers but that certain
numbers for
after
you her